When positioning children relative to other sibling views,
Diğer kardeş görüntülere göre alt görüntüleri konumlandırırken
you can add constraints on their position.
konumlarına kısıtlama ekleyebilirsiniz.
For example, one TextView must be above another TextView,
Örneğin, bir TextView diğer TextView'in üzerinde olması gerekir veya
or one ImageView must be to the left of another TextView.
bir ImageView diğer TextView'in solunda olması gerekir gibi.
All these constraints remind me of making a seating chart for
Tüm bu kısıtlamalar bana akşam yemeği partisi için oturma çizelgesi
a dinner party.
yapmayı hatırlattı.
We do have our birthday party celebration coming up, so
Önümüzde bir doğumgünü kutlaması var,
let's look at the seating chart for that.
hadi onun oturma çizelgesine bakalım.
We invited all these people over for
Tüm bu insanları yemeğe davet ettik.
dinner But there are constraints on where people want to sit.
Fakat insanların oturmak istediği yerlerle ilgili kısıtlamalar var.
Some people must sit next to their best friend.
Bazı insanlar en iyi arkadaşlarının yanına oturmalılar.
Other people have what you might call frenemies.
Diğerlerinin dost-düşmanları var.
So, they might not want to sit next to certain people.
Yani, onlar bazı kişilerin yanına oturmak istemeyebilir.
So, taking into account all of that, I came up with this proposed layout.
Yani, tüm bunları hesaba katarak bu önerdiğim düzeni buldum.
Kunal, Ben, and Kagure are up here.
Kunal, Ben ve Kagure burada olacak.
Natalie, Lyla, and me are down here And Amy, Omoju and Jenny are in this corner.
Natalie, Lyla ve ben buradayız. Amy, Omoju ve Jenny ise bu köşede.
So could we build this seating arrangement in XML using TextViews and
Peki bu oturma düzenini XML'de TextView ve Relative Layout
a relative layout?
kullanarak oluşturabilir miyiz?
We know how to position views in corners.
Görüntüleri köşelere nasıl koyacağımızı biliyoruz.
So the Lyla TextView would be aligned to the parent's left edge and bottom edge.
O zaman Lyla TextView'i üst görünümün sol alt köşesine hizalanacak.
The Jennie TextView would be aligned to the parent's right edge and bottom edge.
Jennie TextView'i üst görünümün sağ alt köşesine hizalanacak.
For Ben we would align them to the top edge of the parent.
Ben'i ise üst görünümün üst köşesine hizalayacağız.
By the way, we're assuming that the parent is the full width and
Bu arada, üst görünüm tam genişlik ve yükseklik olacağı için
So back to Ben.
Ben'e geri dönelim.
He's aligned to the top of the parent.
Üst görünümün üstüne hizalı.
We also want to center him horizontally.
Ayrıca onu yatay olarak ortalamak istiyoruz.
And formerly, you might call these three views the anchor views.
Bu üç görünüme referans görünümler diyebiliriz.
Because everyone else is positioned relative to these people.
Çünkü diğerleri bu kişilere göre konumlandırılacak.
And these people won't move, regardless of where everyone else is sitting.
Ve kim nerede oturursa otursun, bu kişiler hareket etmeyecek.
So let's add another person.
Peki, bir kişi daha ekleyelim.
We have Kunal here, who's located to the left of Ben.
Burada Kunal var, yeri Ben'in solunda.
But how do we express that in XML?
Bunu XML'de nasıl ifade ederiz?
Well, there's no specific attribute that says that a view should be to the left
Bir görüntü Ben adlı görüntünün solunda olmalı diyebileceğimiz belirli bir
of a view named Ben.
öznitelik yok.
All the Android attribute names are general so
Tüm Android öznitelik adları geneldir,
that it works for any use case that you'd want.
bu yüzden istediğiniz herhangi bir kullanım durumunda çalışır.
We want to position Kunal to the left of Ben, but
Kunal'ı Ben'in soluna koymak istiyoruz fakat
we don't know of any existing attribute names that can do that.
bunu yapabilecek öznitelik isimlerinden hiçbirini bilmiyoruz.
Luckily though,
Neyse ki,
RelativeLayout has an attribute that says android: layout_toLeftof.
RelativeLayout'un android: layout_toLeftof diye bir özniteliği bulunuyor.
This means that the Kunal text view should be to the left of some view.
Bu demektir ki, Kunal TextView'i bir görüntünün solunda olmalı.
And the way that we specify some view is to use view IDs.
Ve bunu view ID kullanarak yapıyoruz.
We can assign view ID names to any view.
Herhangi bir görüntüye view ID atayabiliriz.
They don't have to be specifically addressed for RelativeLayout.
Özellikle RelativeLayout için belirtilmiş olması gerekmiyor.
They could be located within a RelativeLayout, or a LinearLayout, or
Bir RelativeLayout, LinearLayout veya herhangi bir
any other view group.
görüntü grubu içerisinde olabilir.
So on the Ben TextView, we can add this attribute, android:id.
Yani Ben TextView'i üzerine şu özniteliği ekleyebiliriz, android:id.
The value of it is the ID name.
Onun değeri ise ID ismi.
The format starts with @ symbol, @ refers to a resource in our Android app.
Format @ sembolü ile başlar, @ Android uygulamamızdaki bir kaynağa atıf yapar.
We've also seen this @symbol for referring to images in our app.
Bu @ sembolünü uygulamamızdaki resimlere atıf yaparken görmüştük.
For example app Drawable.
Örneğin Drawable uygulaması.
Then we specify the resource type.
Sonra kaynak türünü belirleriz.
In this case, the resource type is an id.
Bu durumda, kaynak türü bir id.
We also add the plus symbol because this is the first time we're
Artı işaretini de ekliyoruz çünkü bu id'yi ilk defa
declaring this id.
bildiriyoruz.
This is the name that we chose for the Ben TextView.
Ben TextView'i için bu adı seçtik.
We call it ben_text_view.
Ben_text_view dedik.
The basic requirements are that the name can't have any spaces.
Temel gereklilik isimde hiç boşluk olmamasıdır.
That's why we use underscore symbols here.
Bu nedenle alt çizgi kullanıyoruz.
Numbers are fine though.
Sayılar da kullanılabilir.
So in this case we give Ben the ID of ben_text_view.
Bu durumda Ben'e ben_text_view ID'sini verdik.
That way we can refer to it later.
Böylece daha sonra ona atıfta bulunabiliriz.
So on the Kunal TextView we can add the attribute layout_toLeftof and
Kunal TextView'i için layout_toLeftof özniteliğini ekleyip
we can say it's to the left of the Ben TextView.
Ben TextView'inin solunda diyebiliriz.
We refer to the ID for the Ben TextView using @id.
Ben TextView ID'sine @id kullanarak atıf yapıyoruz.
We don't need to use the plus symbol because We've already defined that ID.
Artı işareti kullanmak zorunda değiliz çünkü zaten o ID'yi tanımladık.
This is the second time we're using the ID.
Bu ID'yi ikinci kez kullanıyoruz.
When you come up with view ID names, make sure that they're all unique names.
ID isimleriyle karşılaşırsanız hepsinin farklı isim olmasına dikkat edin.
Usually, picking something related to the content inside of it is helpful.
Genellikle, içeriğe bağlı bir isim seçmek yardımcı olur.
Okay, cool, so that's how you position Kunal to the left of Ben.
Tamam, harika, işte bu şekilde Kunal'ı Ben'in soluna yerleştirebiliriz.
Now, say, for example, we want to position Omoju above Jennie.
Şimdi, diyelim ki, Omoju'yu Jennie'nin üstüne koyacağız.
Since we're going to need to refer to Jennie,
Jennie'ye atıfta bulunmamız gerekeceği için
we should create an ID for Jennie.
Jennie için ID oluşturmamız gerekli.
On the Jennie TextView, we specify this attribute and give it this value.
Jennie TextView'i için, bu ismi belirledik ve bu değeri verdik.
The ID name is jennie_text_view.
ID ismi jennie_text_view.
On the Omoju TextView, we add this attribute.
Omoju TextView'i için bu özniteliği ekliyoruz.
This says that Omoju should be positioned above the jennie_text_view.
Diyor ki, Omoju jennie_text_view'inin üzerine konumlanmalı.
And this is the ID that we created up here.
Ve burada oluşturduğumuz ID ise bu.
Let's look at the XML layout.
XML Layout'a bakalım.
We have a relative layout where the width and height are match_parent.
Elimizde bir RelativeLayout var, genişlik ve yüksekliği ise match_parent.
Then we have the lyla_text_view.
Bir de lyla_text_view var.
It's aligned to the parent's bottom left corner, and
Alt sol köşeye hizalanmış durumda
that's what we see down here.
ve burada da öyle görüyoruz.
Then we have the jennie_text_view.
Sonra jennie_text_view var.
It's aligned to the parents bottom right corner.
O da alt sağ köşede.
So that's over here.
Yani burada.
Then we have the ben_text_view.
Sonra ben_text_view var.
And it's aligned to the top edge of the parent.
O da üst köşede.
It's also centered horizontally.
Ayrıca yatayda ortalandı.
These are the anchor views and
Bunlarda referans görüntüler ve
now we can position the other views around them.
diğer görüntüleri onların etrafında konumlandırabiliriz.
Notice that for each of the views I already went ahead and added an ID.
Dikkat edin, diğer görüntüler için daha önceden ID ekledim.
So this is the Ben TextView ID.
Yani bu Ben TextView ID'si.
Then we can position the Kunal TextView to the left of Ben.
Sonra Kunal TextView'ini Ben'in soluna konumlandırabiliriz.
I align Kunal to the top of the parent, and to the left of the Ben TextView.
Kunal'ı en üste ve Ben TextView'in soluna hizalıyorum.
I use the view ID for Ben right here.
İşte burada Ben için ID kullanıyorum.
Omoju is aligned to the right edge of the parent, and
Omoju sağ köşeye hizalı ve
above the Jenny TextView.
Jenny TextView'inin üstünde.
Okay cool.
Harika.
So there's more friends to position correctly in this layout.
Bu layout'ta yerleştirilecek daha fazla arkadaş var.
In the instructor notes below we've provided you a link
Aşağıdaki ders notlarında sizlere başlangıç kodlarıyla birlikte
to the XML Visualizer with some initial code already in there.
XML görüntüleyici linkini paylaştık.
Go ahead and modify the XML so
Devam edin ve XML'i düzenleyin ve
that we can achieve this desired layout for everyone.
herkesin istediği yere oturmasını sağlayalım.
Some of the views are already positioned incorrectly, so
Bazı görüntüler yanlış olarak konumlandırıldı, yani
you'll need to fix those.
bunları düzeltmeniz gerekecek.
By the way, we just introduced a ton of new attributes.
Bu arada, bir sürü yeni öznitelik gösterdik.
But don't feel like you have to memorize all of them.
Ama bunların hepsini ezberlemeniz gerektiğini düşünmeyin.
You can always look them up at any time.
İstediğiniz zaman açıp bakabilirsiniz.
You can just search for a relativelayout, layout params.
Relativelayout, layout params şeklinde arama yapabilirsiniz.
So these are all the XML attributes that you can put on a child view
Alt görünümde RelativeLayout içerisine koyabileceğiniz tüm bu XML öznitelikleri
within a RelativeLayout so that the RelativeLayout knows how to lay it out.
sayesinde RelativeLayout nasıl düzenleyeceğini biliyor.
Here are some that you're already familiar with.
Aşina olduklarınızdan birkaçı şöyle.
Layout_above, alignParentbottom, alignParentright and so on.
Layout_above, alignParentbottom, alignParentright ve saire.
Note that for
Şunu da not edin,
However, when you're developing an app in Android Studio you
Lakin, Android Studio'da uygulama geliştiriyorsanız
should be able to use all of these.
bunların hepsini kullanabilmelisiniz.